Hello, everyone. Welcome
to another session
on lung mechanics today,
specifically focusing
on the pressures
acting on the system.
Okay, I am Vishwa Rajapal,
again, Associate Professor
in Biomedical Sciences,
and let's dive in. So
here are the learning
objectives. To distinguish
between pulmonary and
alveolar ventilation in normal
respiratory physiology, to
apply muscle anatomy involved
in the generation of
pulmonary pressures, to
deconstruct lung mechanics
generating three key
pressures, intrapleural,
alveolar, and transpulmonary.
to chart the functional
relationship between these
three types of pressures
in a combined fashion and
understanding how is it
relevant for clinical conditions
such as restrictive and
obstructive diseases.
We'll also see other conditions
as well whenever possible.
Okay,
so back to ventilation,
well, we introduced in
the previous session
on the basic concepts,
what is ventilation,
what is diffusion, you
know, at a broad level.
And later, other
sessions will deal much
greater into that,
into these. So we'll
again expand more
on ventilation here.
okay okay so lung volumes
and capacities just as a
refresher to bring that
back in your memory what is
what are lung volumes and
what are lung capacities
there are this tidal volume
which is the normal breathing
that we saw in the previous
session on the basic
concepts and then inspiratory
reserve volume the deep
inspiration that we take
and then expiratory reserve
volume more than the normal
breathing expiration.
And then we have, below
that we have residual volume
which cannot be breathed out,
right, with our voluntary
effort. And then when we
combine a couple of these,
then we get capacities such
as inspiratory capacity,
vital capacity, or sometimes
forced vital capacity,
and then functional residual
capacity, and then total
lung capacity. Okay, with
that uh with that uh concept
those concepts back in our
mind behind let us move
on uh focusing more on
the ventilatory mechanics
ventilation ventilation it's
a result of mechanical forces
associated with chest wall
and the lungs so it's like
a battle a good battle that's
happening between both so
remember that lung is an
elastic structure that
collapses like a balloon okay
imagine you're blowing a balloon
and that's that's like a
lung okay and it expels
all its air through the
trachea whenever there is no
force to keep it inflated
okay all its air means all its
that is possible there are
no attachments between the
lungs and the walls of the
chest cage really speaking
it's not like stuck uh to
any tissue um in the body
except there on the top
except where it is suspended
at its hilum from the
media stenum uh the middle
section of the chest cavity
so uh except that reason lungs
is like like floating
floating balloon okay um it's
interesting imagine. So it's
floating in the thoracic
cavity surrounded by a
thin layer of pleural fluid
that lubricates the movement
of the lungs within the
cavity. Okay, thin layer of
pleural fluid, about which
we'll look in greater
detail. So what's happening?
Here you have forces in,
let me take a better
color. All right.
So there is, there are
forces pushing inside and
there are forces from the
diaphragm pushing up during
when breathing out
diaphragm moves up breathing
in diaphragm moves down
okay when you're breathing
in the chest expands and
then breathing out it it
goes in okay we'll into the
dynamics in more detail.
All right.
So again, refreshing on
pulmonary and alveoli
ventilation. What are the
differences between these
pulmonary ventilation,
which is sometimes referred
to as minute ventilation
or minute volume. Okay.
Minute ventilation or
minute volume. It's a gross
ventilation per minute which
is the product of tidal
volume times respiratory
rate that's it you've got to
remember this tidal volume
times respiratory rate um
i'm not i'm not saying
uh you know equality
but just as a as a
relative comparison
in the heart we saw cardiac
output is the product
of stroke volume times heart
rate right stroke volume
times heart rate is cardiac
output, drawing parallel
to, that's liquid, here
it's gas, and here it's
the prime pulmonary
ventilation, which is the
product of tidal volume and
respirator rate, you know,
it's, it's something to
remember, something that helps
you, if it helps you, it
helps, it'll remember easily.
Alveolar ventilation.
Alveolar ventilation is the
fresh air that reaches gas
exchange areas of the lungs.
Gas exchange areas of the
lungs. So that means you've
got to remove the dead
space. So it's only the gas
exchange areas, not all areas
of the lungs. So when you
subtract the dead space,
then what you get is from
the pulmonary ventilation,
if you subtract tidal volume,
you get alveolar ventilation.
concept to remember.
The dead space is physiological
dead space volume and you have
so we saw what alveolar
ventilation means it's the total
volume of new air entering
the alveoli and adjacent
gas exchange areas each
minute and if you if you give
some numbers to this the
tidal volume let's say if you
give 500 ml and dead space
if you give approximately
150 ml and respiratory rate
if you give 15 breaths per
minute it could be like 20
to 12 excuse me 12 to 18 in
adults maybe uh 15 let's
say if you give average and
then what is albaba ventilation
um 350 times 15 you get
5250 ml per minute okay 5
.2 5.3 liters per minute in
average so note that in an
individual with healthy lungs,
the anatomical and the
physiological dead spaces are
nearly equal because why? All
the alveoli are functional
in normal lung. But in
some pathologies, what
happens is the physiological
dead space may be as much as
10 times the volume of
anatomical dead space, which
means it could go up to one
to two liters. So typically,
it's the physiological
dead space and the
anatomical dead space
are close to one another.
But in pathological
conditions, the
physiological dead space
can be as high as 10.
You know, it could
go up to that
level. So just to
give you a context.
Okay, let's move on. We've got
a lot of good
concepts to cover.
So summarizing ventilation,
you have tidal volume on
the top, you have total
ventilation, you have anatomical
dead space, as I said, it
could be a range of 150 ml
and then frequency, 15
frequencies, respiratory rate.
Alveolar gas could be 3000
ml. Alveolar ventilation
is 5.2 meters per
minute, I saw. You don't
worry about this ratio,
you will learn that later.
And then the pulmonary blood
flow, you'll learn later. Okay,
so this is the context.
So this is one single
alveolus, right?
We'll look into what's
happening in the alveolus,
outside alveolus. We
won't go into the
perfusion, that comes later.
All right, now,
proper pressures
acting on the system, right?
Okay, what happens
when we breathe?
What happens when we breathe?
The lungs can be expanded
and contracted in two ways.
One, downward movement.
The other is downward
or upward, okay?
Downward or upward.
And then the
other is forward,
forward or backward.
So the downward or
upward movement of the
diaphragm to lengthen or
shorten the chest cavity.
And then by elevation
or depression of the
ribs, it helps to increase
or decrease the anterior
-posterior diameter
of the chest cavity.
Anterior-posterior diameter
So you have chest expanding
during inhalation or
inspiration. This is the
sternum, this is the ribs,
and lungs, and all the
areas you see, diaphragm
contracts, key, very
important thing to remember.
Diaphragmatic contraction is
crucial for normal inspiration.
And then diaphragmatic
relaxation is
crucial for normal
expiration or exhalation.
And chest contraction happens.
While here, chest
expansion happens. Okay.
Okay.
Next.
Muscles, what are the
muscles that cause lung
expansion and contraction?
One we saw, diaphragm, here
it is, diaphragm flattening
during inspiration.
When air flows in, that is
inspiration or inhalation,
diaphragm flattens. That
means diaphragm contracts.
And the opposite happens
when air flows out,
diaphragm dooms up
and relaxes. And ribs
move down and in. Here
ribs move up and out.
So this is the most
important muscle, arguably
the most important
muscle of inspiration,
the diaphragm. And then
the elevated, there is
also, during inspiration,
increased vertical
diameter, we saw in the
previous figure too.
And then increased AP
diameter thickness by
approximately greater than or
equal to 20% it can happen.
Okay? The anterior posterior
diameter thickness.
Now on the top right you
see a figure. What is this?
It's an igloo.
In the cold countries
you can see.
So imagine an igloo without
a closed door. Okay,
imagine a closed door. And
on the top, you have chimney.
Why do we have
this figure here?
So, if you, the
internal, so it, it helps
mimic or helps us
understand how lungs
can work. In this
figure, in this top right
figure, you see,
it's, it's, it burns,
the chimney burns, and
air has to be exchanging
inside and outside.
So imagine, again,
a doorless igloo or a
closed door igloo with
a chimney pump and
an internal fire that
models the alveolar
ventilation and perfusion.
So the pump's speed
represents the ventilation
rate, the ventilation
rate of the breathing.
And then that refreshes
the air because air
refreshing is important,
circulation is
important. And the size
of the fire represents
perfusion. You'll learn
that later. And that
helps exchange oxygen
and carbon dioxide.
And altering either, you
know, predictably, altering
either of these predictably
changes the air composition
and that illustrates the
lung physiology. And the
interesting thing to note is
if you imagine heart, there
is an inflow and outflow.
There is a pulmonary venous
inflow of blood into the
left side of the heart and
it goes back to circulation
and it comes back to the
right atrium and again
it goes out. So there is
circulation that both in and
out is happening unless there
is pathological mixing like
congenital heart defects.
So many varieties are
there which mixes blood. So
now the gut if you take,
there is an oral cavity,
esophagus and then it goes
all the way down to small and
large intestine and then
there is an intake and then
there is exit. but lungs
and they are in those cases
there are two separate you
know two separate mechanisms
to enter and exit but here
in the lungs there is only
one the airflow has to come
in through the same and
the airflow has to go out
to the same you know cavity
pipe the trachea and the
nasal cavity or oral cavity
that's why this igloo
helps us understand so keep
that in mind as you learn
not just this lecture but
you know several other
respiratory system lectures and
concepts to count
pathological and physiological
okay we have multiple other
things to cover so uh you
know so i'm not getting
into detail of this analogy
uh let's focus on the
concepts that you need to
understand for the purpose
of your understanding and
exams muscles of inspiration
what are the muscles we
saw diaphragm crucial right
and we saw we saw diaphragm
and then yeah so the key
muscles are the principal
and accessory and the
left is principal external
intercostals which help
elevate the ribs you see the
arrow and then you have
interchondral part of
intercostals not all intercostal
muscles interchondral part
of intercostal muscles
that also helps elevate the
ribs and then you have
diaphragm that dooms, descend
and then increasing the
longitudinal dimension of
the chest and elevating
lower ribs we saw you know
a short while ago. And
accessory muscles are necessary
during exerted inspirations,
strenocledomastoid,
scaliness and you know those
muscles. You have learned
these muscles in anatomy
so we are just trying
to spot and point out what
are relevant for us here.
We will look again.
External intercostals, right?
What does it do? External
intercostals help us help
with the upward and forward
movement of the ribs.
And bucket handle motion
is something. So imagine,
before that, here's the
vertebra, here is the sternum
and you can see there's a
lateral increase in volume
okay and here again anterior
increase in volume so the
example used is a bucket if
you take that if you take
some water or something with
a bucket look at the movement
of the handle right it's
not always it's not fully
vertical it's not fully
horizontal there's a lateral
increase in volume and that's
what happens with the ribs
and also water happens with
the ribs with the sternum
particularly there is an
anterior and increase in volume
just like how you know in
ancient times or even in
some other some parts of
some countries there is still
usage of this public water
system where the handle is
pulled that leads to an
anterior increase in pulling.
So that is, remember
these two examples to
remember how these
chest structures move.
And similar to the pump handle
motion and bucket
handle motion,
the intercostals help with the
contraction and it helps move.
They are used both
during normal quiet
breathing and also under
respiratory distress.
Okay, and the internal
intercostals are relaxed and
then that raises an
increase in volume of the
ribcage and abdomen. And
abdominal contents are pushed
downward and the ribs are
lifted upward and outward,
increasing the volume
of the thoracic cavity.
Okay, so again I repeat,
abdominal contents are pushed
up downward and the ribs
are, what are we talking
about, lung expansion and
contraction. So, lung expansion
is during inspiration,
abdominal contents are pushed
downward, and the ribs are
lifted upward and downward,
excuse me, upward and
outward, that increases the
volume of the thoracic
cavity. So, there's a nice
cooperation happening between
thorax and abdomen during every
single breath, thanks to
our diaphragm in between.
Okay, what else do we have?
Alright.
Okay, you remember that.
In resting breathing,
inspiration is an active
process, but expiration
is a passive process,
normal expiration,
or mainly passive,
or mostly passive.
Resting breathing,
inspiration is an active one.
Expiration is typically,
generally it is passive.
But in vigorous breathing,
for any reason, if you
have to have a vigorous
breathing, both inspiration
and expiration are active.
And what happens during
the inspiration, diaphragm
plus accessory muscles
are used for inspiration.
And in expiration,
typically it's normally
it is quiet breathing,
but here accessory
muscles of expiration
are used. Okay, I
just put a picture
here to remember, to
remind that, you know,
the vigorous breathing
can happen not only
in pathological
conditions. Even in
conditions where people
go to extreme settings,
such as very, very
difficult Everest,
Mount Everest or other peaks,
mountaineering in difficult,
very high elevation.
So those are some of
the situations where
vigorous breathing
can happen. in fact i
personally have an
experience um last year i
was at i was at uh in
the top of himalayas
5630 meters high which
is about 18 500 feet
um i experienced even
a casual walk a casual
step was not normal
it was it was i had to
breathe it was hard
breathing it was difficult
breathing So we have
extra support systems,
you know,
all the gears and
O2 as needed, etc.
But what we need to understand
is, so these extreme
scenarios also can trigger
these accessory muscles.
And it was a wonderful
experience. If anyone is
interested, I'm happy to
expand more on that offline.
Okay, moving on.
So, refreshing on the
different muscles, on
the left, we already saw
what muscles, external
intercostals, intracondral
part of the internal
intercostals, and you
have diaphragm, and
then accessory muscles
under special scenarios.
On the right, you have
muscle of expiration,
and during expiration is a
normally passive recoil of
the lungs, passive process,
but it's an active process
when other muscles chip
in in vigorous breathing
scenarios, which includes
internal intercostal,
subdominal muscles, rectus
abdominis, external oblique,
internal oblique, transversus
abdominis. so on okay now
the next point to remember
is the muscles of inspiration
and expiration the major
muscles and what is
their relevance connection
with the minute volume remember
we read we saw minute
volume minute volume is also
known as minute ventilation
which is also known as
pulmonary ventilation and
how is it calculated it's
the product of tidal volume
times respiratory relate
TV or VT times RR. Now
this slide tells us that in
the bottom if you see minute
volume is already know is
already the amount of air
breathed in and out round
trip in one minute in one
minute so that's the liters
per minute numbers here um
that on the on the right
side you see liters per
minute number right these
numbers indicate that the
minute volume indicate the
minute volume at which the
various muscles on the left
begin to contribute to
breathing in a healthy adult.
These numbers,
sternocleidomastroids and
anterior serotonin,
these begin to work when
the minute volume goes
high, as high as like
50 liters per minute,
they start working.
Spina serractor, strapezius,
posterior, those neck
muscles work when the minute
volume that is necessary
to breathe is 100 liters
per minute. Either the
respiratory rate is too high
or tidal volume is too high.
Whatever is happening,
that's when these muscles
kick in those are muscles
of inspiration again diaphragm
resting condition external
intercostals you know
resting and sometimes more
than resting too and muscles
of expiration or internal
intercostals again it's
in the resting condition
and abdominus abdominal
muscles at 40 liters per minute
now pathologically what
happens in diseases where
the airways are partially
obstructed or movement of the
lungs are restricted the
muscles become active and
at lower minute
volumes. Even at lower
minute volumes,
pathological conditions,
the airways, these
muscles become
active, functional
for this purpose.
Okay,
moving on.
To summarize, what
are all the muscles?
We have some summery in colors.
So you have on both
the figures on the
left side you have
a figure with golden
color muscle and
blue color muscle.
So let's see what does
gold indicate. The most
rostral and dorsal
subsets of the external
intercostal muscles, which
are golden in color here.
And they,
as well as the parasternal
subset of the internal
intercostal muscles, they
have an inspiratory mechanical
advantage. On the right
side, you see mostly caudal
subset of the internal
intercostals, which are in
blue here, and the caudal
ventral subset of the external
intercostal, which are
in gold color here, and
the triangular sternum
muscle, or the transverse
therassus, they have an
expiratory mechanical advantage.
So, and then you have
other muscles, you know,
and the diaphragm and
the abdominals, etc. So
in the middle you see
bucket handle and water
pump effects, remember
sternum moves and then
you have the ribs also
moving in this fashion.
So it's just to
refresh your memory.
And elastic recoil
is expiration under
resting condition,
diaphragm is relaxed.
And in exercise or conditions
like asthma, during
expiration what happens?
Abdominals are contracted,
diaphragm is relaxed, and
then the elastic recoil of the
lungs, chest, wall, and
abdominal structures happen.
Okay, I'm trying to see if
there's anything else to add.
We can move on.
Okay, and then there
are other muscles
also, we said, that
come into business.
Moving on.
What are the factors
affecting diaphragm
function? Diaphragm being
the crucial, one of the
most important muscles
for peaceful breathing.
If something happens
to diaphragm, that's a
problem. And both
physiological and
pathological conditions
where diaphragm could go
to extra steps, extra
functional necessity.
So in the last session, we
saw paradoxical movement
or ascites or pregnancy
or obesity conditions.
functional residual capacity
decreases. Remember,
FRC decreases.
And those are the
situations. What is FRC?
Recap, FRC is the sum
of, it's the total sum of
residual volume and the
expiratory residual volume.
So RV plus ERV, that's
functional residual
capacity. So here what
happens, functional residual
capacity may decrease. So we
have to remember diaphragm
may be impacted by this
and other scenarios.
Okay, moving on,
what are the other
pressures? What are key
pressures acting
on the system? Very
important, okay? Let's
focus even more here.
The factors that affect
the pressures, right?
Three different types of
pressures. One is intercalorie
pressure, alveolar
pressure, and pulmonary
pressure. Before that,
on the left side, you
see absolute pressures
versus relative pressures.
The units,
you know, millimeters of
mercury is what we use
for regular blood pressure
measurement, etc. So
that's conventional. But
for our learning purposes,
we will use centimeters of
water, which is not very
conventional in our
general clinical practice,
you know,
daily practice. But it's
useful. So it was even
more useful, particularly
in the past when researchers
studying these fundamental
concepts to even
understand how the lungs
work, they had to use,
they didn't rely on the
mercury manometers because
they were less sensitive
than the water manometers.
So they used centimeters
of water for measuring
it and, you know, it
helped them very well.
And in the modern
standards, mercury is more
hazardous than water.
We know that. So for our
purposes, we will focus
on centimeters of water.
And if you see, the key
point here in this slide is
there is a gradient. There
is a barometric pressure.
There is a gradient.
there is a low the pleural
pressure is very low on the
top apex than the bottom
it's still negative in
the bottom but it is much
more negative on the top
okay and the minus five is
average that's what we're
going to focus on okay
minus five is what we will
talk as alveolar pressure
and that's because
gravity reasons right um
that's because um sorry
yeah um that's because
of gravity and posture
okay for example if someone
is doing yoga upside
down that will change
these pressure dynamics
in an upside down yoga
like headstand that
will change the dynamics
or in outer space if you
take if you take outer
space the interpleural
gradient would vanish because
there's no gravity or zero
gravity or microgravity
there okay so those are
scenarios that you need
to keep in mind but we'll
talk pretty much under
a terrestrial condition
now okay all right so
intrapleural pressure uh
typically intrapleural pressure
there are two layers of
pleura visceral pleura
and parietal pleura you
already know and there is
pleural fluid between them
and you know the thickness
of this intrapleural
space extremely small um
5 to 35 microns microns so
there is relative vacuum
there at function residual
capacity After a quiet
expiration, the opposing
forces of the lungs trying to
collapse and the chest
wall trying to expand, they
create a negative pressure.
So you have this pressure
going in and out, right?
So there is a balance
that happens in a normal
condition. There is elastic
recoil of the chest wall
tries to pull the chest
outward, and there is elastic
recoil of the lung creates
an inward pulling force. That
balances the intrapleural
pressure, you know, so
that it stays negative.
That is crucial for our
breathing. Otherwise,
there could be
problems, there could
be, you know, treatment
that's necessary,
sometimes even an
interventional procedure.
We'll touch upon
those things a little
bit later. Negative
pleural pressure,
negative pleural pressure,
intrapleural pressure.
How does that happen?
By two mechanisms. One,
the lymphatic system
drains the pleurofluid,
generating a negative
pressure. And then there
is elasticity of the
lungs and the chest wall,
which we already saw. The
elasticity, the bottom
A figure says, elastic
recoil of the lungs.
It tries to recoil,
okay, but the
chest wall is trying
to recoil outside.
The lungs are trying to recoil
inward, so it stays
in balance, okay?
All right.
Let's see. Yeah, so moving on,
if you see on the
top left, there is
negative interpleural
pressure, right?
You can read this and it
will help you understand.
But, so on the left side
is a normal lung, but on
the right side, what
happens? There is a pierce,
there is a damage in the
chest wall. So air has
entered inside, it should
not, entered inside, so it
has collapsed. So this is
called nemothorax. When
air enters inside due to
a stab, trauma, if you've
seen trauma care, you can
see these kinds of patients
with nemothorax. Even after
post-thoracic surgery,
post-cardiothoracic
surgery, you can see such
patients with air entering
in the pleural cavity.
So normally the
pleural pressure is
negative, we know
that's atmospheric.
But in nemothorax, air enters
the pleural space, causing
this pressure to become
less negative. either it
becomes less negative or
it can go positive that's a
danger so in mild nemo
thorax it is less negative
getting equal to atmospheric
pressure which is zero and
in severe tension nemo thorax
it can go highly positive
okay so that is an important
pathological condition
next pathological condition
could be fluid collection
either there is air collection
or there is excessive
fluid collection there is
only optimal level of fluid
that's needed there so
this right-sided x-ray that
you see look at the dramatic
fluid collection there
on the left lung there the
circled area so there is
hardly any air in the bottom
why because or at least
visible because there is so
much of fluid collected so
what do you need to do in
such scenario a procedure
called thoracentesis thoracentesis
is also called pleural
tapping you insert a needle
carefully in the pleural
cavity and start draining
for a good period of time
and then you would carefully
remove it making sure
that air doesn't get trapped
inside okay just to give
you the clinical context
here how important this is
plural space okay um moving
on um both the chest wall
and the lung have elastic
recoil properties you already
know that and how is it
like to just give an analogy
it's like a tug-of-war
right so two for two group
of people pulling the same
rope tightly and simultaneously
that's exactly what's
happening there except
that there is it's a much
more smoother process as you
breathe otherwise you know
now as we speak as we listen
we don't even realize how
long is doing all these
things opposing forces
quietly peacefully right while
you're sleeping it continues
to happen even quieter
right so it's it's beautiful
how the mechanism works.
Okay, moving on.
So now we're going to
focus on single alveolus.
Okay, for learning purposes,
we're going to focus on
single alveolus, what's
happening. At rest, the
inner intra-alveolar
pressure, or just the alveolar
pressure, is zero, and
the external atmospheric
pressure is zero, because
there is a continuum, right?
There is air coming in
and out, so So external
atmosphere and internal
alveolar is zero. This is at
rest, but the pleural
cavity is minus five. That's
necessary to keep it in
balance. Pleural cavity
is minus five, the
intermediate level that we saw.
Let's see further what
happens. At rest, again, what
muscles are working? Just
to give us a, that was
single alveolar context.
Here it is, whole lung
perspective. What's happening
in a single alveolus?
Respiratory muscles are at
rest. Recoil of the lung
and chest wall are equal but
opposite and the pressure
along the tracheobranchial
tree is atmospheric.
There is no air flow
because it's in equilibrium.
Okay.
All right. We'll move on. It
should be self-explanatory.
Now, how does it work?
What is the mechanism
here? What is the
physiological mechanism here?
Boyle's law. In the
first session, I
briefly touched on
Boyle's law. Here it is.
Boyle's law, what is
it? Boyle's law states
that at a constant
temperature, the pressure and
volume of a gas are
inversely proportional.
Long time ago you would have
learned this in physics.
It's at constant
temperature, the
pressure and volume
of a gas are inversely
proportional. So what happened?
P1 V1 equals P2 V2. So
when the, during inhalation
or inspiration, volume
increases, pressure decreases.
Okay, here volume
increases and pressure
decreases. Because there
is a lot more space, the
particles can move
around happily in various
spaces. But here, there
is compression happens,
the volume in exhalation,
volume decreases, and
pressure increases, air
flows out, because there
is a way to flow out.
And that's what happens
here. Decrease pressure,
high volume, high volume,
decrease pressure, and
air moves in and out.
Okay, so keep that
in mind as you
understand this,
these dynamics.
Now, alveolar pressure during
inspiration, very important.
In single alveolos
what happens?
Atmospheric pressure
is always zero, right?
It's always zero.
But the alveolar
pressure, because of
the muscle contraction,
alveolar pressure goes to
minus one and the intrapleural
pressure goes to minus
eight. This is important
for the air to enter inside.
So first, sequentially,
inspiratory muscles contract
and then the thoracic
cavity expands and then
the chest wall pulls on
the pleural space and generates
more negative pressure,
so minus 5 becomes minus 8,
and then the intrapleural
pressure pulls on the
lungs and expands them,
and then the lungs increase
in volume, and then the
P-A drops to sub-atmospheric
levels from 0 to minus 1,
and boom, the air flows
down the gradient until the
gradient is 0, okay? So
now the air has flown in,
okay, let's move on. The
same thing, we are looking in
a single alveolus, but from
a whole lung perspective.
Um, this is the same for
muscle contraction, and
it becomes, alveolar
pressure becomes sub
-atmospheric. So we don't
have to spend more time here.
Um,
we'll use it elsewhere.
So, in summarizing this,
lung force relationships
during inspiration, there's
increase in negativity in
intraplural pressure, and
then there is expansion
of chest wall, causes the
gas in the alveoli to
expand, creating negative
alveolar pressure, Increase
in negative pressure in the
lung, alveoli causes air
to flow inside the lungs.
Expiration, right?
Expiration or exhalation,
what happens? Atmospheric
pressure, always zero.
But the alveolar pressure from
minus one, it reached zero.
And then it has gone even
beyond that, plus one.
That gradient is important.
And the interplural
pressure is getting
back to minus five. So
interpleural pressure, which
was originally minus 5,
went down to minus 8, and
it's now back to minus
5, but the alveolar
pressure, which was negative,
went up to zero, and now it's
positive. So that positive
pressure is necessary
for it to push the air
outside, which is perfused
already with carbon dioxide,
right? More CO2. So that
needs to be expelled out.
So the sequence again on
the right you can read
a muscle relaxation,
thoracic volume declining,
and then PIP from minus
8 to minus 5 and then
the lungs will decrease
in size and then the PA
alveolar pressure will
raise above the atmospheric
pressure from 0 to 1
and air flows outside.
All right,
good.
Again the same thing
from a single alveolar
but from a whole lung
perspective from letters.
So this is the summary.
Again, what else is here?
In the second bullet point,
you can see that the
lung deflation begins and
continues until the recoil
force decreases to again
equal the interferon pressure.
And once this occurs,
the lung system is back
to functional residual
capacity. So that is the
baseline for the functional
residual capacity. And
then up or down happens.
Okay, now we are
getting into another
important concept that
we have to learn. We
have less time.
Transpulmonary pressure.
Transpulmonary pressure is,
so trans airway pressure
and transpulmonary pressures
are kind of similar in
the way it works. They are
different. They both are
difference between pressure
inside versus pressure outside.
But we are, for our
purposes, we are needing to
focus more on transpulmonary
pressure, which is the
difference between, it is a
measure of the four elastic
forces in the lungs that
tend to collapse the lungs
at each instant of respiration,
and that's also called
as the plastic recoil
pressure. It's the difference
between alveolar pressure
minus the pleural pressure.
Okay, pressure is
acting on this system.
Let's understand it
from this perspective.
Let's see if there's
anything else to add here.
So, to trans
-pulmonary pressure,
Yeah, I think that's
it. We can move on.
Yeah, so what we see
here is So what we
see here is on the
top, the left top,
we have
tidal volume, right? Tidal
volume in the beginning
it starts at 0 and it
goes up to 500 ml and then
reaches the peak point and
then comes down at the end
of expiration so this is
the peak of completion of
inspiration and the
beginning of expiration comes
down to zero and it goes
on again and again and
continues now here let's focus
here on the bottom is the
pressure the top is the
volume and here it is
inspiration and here it is
expiration so at the beginning
of inspiration remember
the alveolar pressure was
zero it's nothing different
than what we saw before
we are looking in a different
you know perspective
At the beginning, the
alveolar pressure is zero.
At the peak of inspiration,
which is at the
lowest phase of the
alveolar pressure, it goes
down to, it is at,
let's see, yeah, during
inspiration, it's at minus
2.5, and it goes down,
is that right? What
am I reading here?
Yeah, alveolar pressure
is minus 2.5. But
as it comes back, it
comes back to zero.
And then zero is what?
Atmospheric pressure. So it
goes back to atmospheric
pressure, the continuum.
during expiration the
alveolar pressure goes up to
plus one remember it has to
go up to plus one and then
it has to come back to zero
in parallel what do we see
the pleural pressure the
bottom line is pleural
pressure starts at minus
five goes down at the end of
inspiration to minus eight and
then comes back up increases
increases back to minus
five at the end of the
expiration to This is the
beginning of the inspiration
now. This difference, right?
Trans pulmonary pressure.
Deepest here, and then
here. So all these
regions are trans
pulmonary pressure. This is
crucial for the lungs to
function and balance it.
On the right side,
you have this figure.
At functional recipe
capacity, the trigly
volume, we already saw,
same as the left side.
Sorry.
The pleural pressure,
minus 5, goes down to minus
8, and it's a nice curve
back. there's a concept
of flow which you will
learn more in the later
sessions so this flow
starts at zero goes down to
minus five and then goes
comes back to zero at the
end of inspiration this
middle middle broken line
is inspiration okay
inhalation and then when
expiration happens flow
increases and then decreases
when it comes back to the
end of the expiration.
Similar pattern as alveolar
pressure. Alveolar pressure
starts at 0, goes down to
minus 1, comes back to 0.
And then from 0, it goes
even beyond to 1 sorry about
that, it goes up to 1 and
then comes back to 0. So
even though numbers are
different for flow, the same
pattern of the curves that's
happening. So it's good to
remember, it's useful to
remember that way okay so
inspiration is okay we already
uh um bent over the chart
so what are the key points
in this very important i
would say i would suggest
you to practice this uh you
know especially the left f
especially this part practice
drawing with your hand in
a in a paper or an app or
on the whiteboard however
you like um so that when you
may actually do it you'll
remember you You can remember
even better, you know,
typically, but if you can't
remember without that, go
for it, however you like.
Good.
Let's delete this.
So that's the main thing.
Let's focus on, so
this is the summary.
The summary is outward
elastic recoil of the chest
wall, which is the difference
between the pleural
pressure and the pressure
of the surface of
the chest. this outward
elastic recoil is opposed
by the inward elastic
recoil of the lungs, which
is the difference between
alveolar pressure and
interplural pressure. So
remember this concept.
Furthermore, the trans
-pulmonary pressure, which is
the elastic recoil pressure,
is the difference between
the alveolar pressure and
the interplural pressure.
So these two major
mechanisms balance the inward
flow and outflow flow of
normal ventilation. Let's
see what happens in
pathological conditions.
We already saw some of the
pathologies like nemothorax
and pleural fluid
collection, etc. Let's
look at obstructive and
restrictive lung diseases.
We saw in the first
session, so we're
bringing back these
mechanisms in the
context of the lung
volumes and capacities.
So, in obstructive lung
diseases, for example,
asthma or chronic bronchitis,
You have increased
residual volume and
functional residual capacity.
So, there is obstruction.
So, there is more
residual volume. And then
there is more functional
residual capacity.
Both of these represent
air that is left in the
lung after expiration.
Okay. Now, that is why
because that's the loss of the
ability to develop the
positive alveolar pressure.
Alveolar pressure needs
to go to positive.
Right. But it's not
able to become positive.
That is a problem in
obstructive lung disease.
Restrictive lung disease,
like fibrosis, for instance,
pulmonary fibrosis, what
is happening? Decreased
functional residual capacity.
Here it is increased
residual volume and functional
residual capacity. Here
it is decreased functional
residual capacity and
decreased residual volume.
You see in the figure,
decreased RV, decreased
FRC, and decreased TLC, and
decreased ERV, and VT.
Pretty much everything is
decreased here, right? But you
see here, here tidal volume
is increased, expiratory
reserve volume is
increased, functional residue
capacity is increased, RV
is increased. Except these
three things, others are
increased. But here everything
is decreased. So it's
a good way to remember.
But what is the problem?
It's the decreased
functional residue
capacity is because
there less air
is taken inside
with an inspiration.
There is a problem
more of, you know, air
that's left after the
expiration. Here it
is. Less air is taken
inside inspiration.
And that's because the
loss of the ability of
ability to develop the
negative alveolar pressure.
Alveolar pressure
should go sufficiently
negative. It's not going
because of the pathology.
So that is the problem
in restrictive lung
disease. So these concepts
you have to remember.
All right. We are
getting close to closing
because all these lectures.
We were told to finish
all the lectures by
15 minutes. all the
lectures I don't know
how you know others deal
this but we are told so
I try to stick to that
as much as possible so
a quick quiz here as
inspiration proceeds
the plural pressure
reaches until what number
so I'm going to say the
answer so please pause
right now and think
and come back.
Okay, the answer
is minus eight.
Okay,
minus eight. As
inspiration proceeds,
the pleural pressure
reaches until minus eight
centimeters of water,
typically in a healthy
lung, and then it has
to come back up. Right?
Okay, and why? Because
as the lungs expand,
the recoil pressure
of the lung increases.
The pleural pressure
must fall to oppose the
increasing tendency of
the lungs to collapse.
Okay,
so what all have
we seen so far?
Learning objectives to
distinguish between the
pulmonary and alveolar
ventilation we saw initially.
Then we saw the
muscle anatomy. We
saw what are all the
muscles involved.
Then we saw what mechanics
are involved. What
are the pressures, the
three major pressures,
interchloral, alveolar,
and trans-pulmonary.
We charted them in
a combined fashion,
bringing the concept of
transformative pressure,
and the volumes,
the flow, and so on.
Then we connected these two,
some representative
pathologies.
Now, you want some practice
questions, right?
Here they are.
So, there is, scholar
products should have some
questions. There are some
books. I have the links here.
There are some books here,
books dedicated to case
studies, books dedicated
to, you know, like I
think the Rhodes and Bell
Medical Physiologists here,
maybe Borden and Bell
PEP. So you can please
use your NYIT login.
That will take you to the
chapter, and then maybe
towards the end of
the chapter, you will
have some questions and
with answers, with
rationales too, generally.
Okay, I hope these will
be very helpful and
important, so please
do practice a lot of
questions, okay? And
these are the references,
different textbooks
including ScholarRx
and we have some
letters to Guyton
and Hall this year's
material as well.
The full book link
is available in
the library with
this NYT login.
I think that's it. So
thank you everyone and
please let me know if
you have any questions.
So I'm just scrolling
back. So this figure
is important. Okay,
basically what are
all, everything is
important of course, but
let's try to narrow
it down even further.
So transcolonary pressure, try
to remember this even better.
All the different, three
different types of pressures.
So go with learning
objectives, right?
If you focus by
learning objectives,
you will be able to
get a better sense.
And this mechanism is
important. What happens during
rest in a single alveolus,
what's happening during
inspiration, what's happening
during expiration. expiration
and then we looked into
the opposing forces of the
chest wall and example
pathologies what happens and
then intraplural pressure
more on intraplural pressure
and then we saw
diaphragm how the how
the sternum moves how
the ribs move right
using those analogies.
And what are all the muscles,
that muscles are important.
Okay, so please do
remember those muscles.
And minute volume is
also, I learned that.
And then the formulae, we saw
some formulae before this,
right?
Yes,
yes, diaphragmatic
movement. And then,
yeah, these are some of the
basic numbers. you've learned
before and here and this
family do this do do
remember this is also important
and of course this is the
first session this is also
very important okay definitely
this these are expected
questions will be can be
expected definitely this
because these are fundamental
core concepts we want you
all to remember and learn
which will be very valuable
both for your clinical practice
and also your board exams
all right and that's pretty
much it thank you everybody
i really appreciate your
support and please feel
free to contact me with any
questions we all want you to
really succeed and i really
look forward to your
wonderful successes thank you